<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Feareful neuues of thunder and lightning with the terrible effects thereof, which Almighty God sent on a place called Oluestone, in the county of Glocester the 28. of Nouember last : hauing prefixt before it, a short discourse, concerning two other admirable accidents that soone after ensued / truely related by P.S. ; and dedicated vnto the Kings Most Excellent Maiestie.</title>
            <author>P. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11249</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1678</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21359845</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21359845</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23950</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11249)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23950)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1713:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Feareful neuues of thunder and lightning with the terrible effects thereof, which Almighty God sent on a place called Oluestone, in the county of Glocester the 28. of Nouember last : hauing prefixt before it, a short discourse, concerning two other admirable accidents that soone after ensued / truely related by P.S. ; and dedicated vnto the Kings Most Excellent Maiestie.</title>
                  <author>P. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld, for Frauncis Burton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D³.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Providence and government of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23950:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23950:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FEAREFVL NEVVES. Of Thunder and Lightning, with the <hi>terrible effects thereof, which Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> God ſent on a place called <hi>Olueſtone,</hi> in the <hi>county of</hi> Gloceſter <hi>the 28. of Nouember laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hauing prefixt before it, a ſhort diſcourſe, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning two other admirable accidents that ſoone after enſued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Truely related by</hi> P. S.</p>
            <p>And dedicated vnto the Kings moſt excellent <hi>Maieſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by <hi>G. Eld,</hi> for <hi>Frauncis Burton.</hi> 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:23950:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23950:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt puiſſant, potent, and <hi>Maiestious, my dread Soueraigne Iames</hi> by the grace of God, of great <hi>Britaine, France, and</hi> Ireland <hi>King defendor of the Faith: the Great</hi>-Commaunder of the Weſt, and North-weſt parts of the <hi>World; Grace, and peace from God our Father, and</hi> from our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, vnto all happineſſe: in <hi>this life, godlineſſe, and righteouſneſſe, and in the life to come, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality and glorie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt puiſſant King, my dread and deare Soueraigne, in moſt humble and ſubmiſſe manner, I your highneſſe moſt duetifull, and loyall Subiect, do herein preſent vnto your excellent Maieſty, the true report of a moſt fearefull accident, which Almighty God the King of kings, and Lord of Lords, ſent among vs, your Highneſſe poore ſubiects at <hi>Olueſtone</hi> in the county of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> on Thurſday beeing the 28. of Nouember laſt: whereof I (your Maieſties ſaid ſubiect) was both an eare, and an eye witneſſe. The power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and admirable workes of God are for none more fit, and profitable, then for the Kings of the earth, whom the God of heauen, hath ſubſtituted next vnder himſelfe, to order and rule the ſeuerall ſocieties of men, in promoting piety, and preſeruing iuſtice: foraſmuch as next vnto the word, and the appendances thereof, (the moſt effectuall meanes) nothing doth, or can more effectually frame, or hauing framed, can more conſtantly continue them in the manage, and performance of all kingly duties, then the ſerious and often meditation of Gods wonderful workes, in the whole frame of the world, &amp; the ſeuerall parts, and
<pb facs="tcp:23950:3"/>portions of it. For as hyſtories, which are the remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of time, and ſucceſſes in time, are for all men meete, and commodious, but eſpecially for Kings, Potentates, and great perſonages, their volumes beeing therefore well denominated, and called theirs; <hi>Principum bonorum, et he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roum libri,</hi> good Kings, and great councellers bookes: ſo the large volume of Gods workes are open, and ſet before all, but for none ſo fit, and profitable, as for their Maieſties, that repreſent vnto vs the maieſtie and power of almighty God. That as the beames of Gods glory ſhine in them, more then in others, ſo they before, and more then others ſhould amire, and reuerence the beames of his glory, and greatnes in heauen, and earth, that hath made them ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and great on earth. And if the knowledge of all the great, and admirable workes of God, be ſo neceſſary for all Kings, then the ſeuerall euents and ſucceſſes that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and extraordinarily fall our, &amp; come to paſſe in their ſeuerall territories, and kingdomes, are in no ſorte to be neglected, but ſo much the more to be remembred, and reuerenced, as God hath therein come more neerer vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then vnto others kings, &amp; hath as it were ſpoken firſt, and more particularly vnto them, that thereof they might make firſt &amp; moſt eſpecially vnto themſelues, a heauenly and chriſtianly vſe: humbly, and heartily to commit, and commend themſelues, and their eſtates, to his ouerſwaying and all ruling prouidence; <hi>That beareth rule ouer the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of men and giueth it to whomſoeuer he will.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4.29.</note> And being thus deuoted perſonally, they may with all deuotion, and care, (according to the truſt committed vnto them) order and direct, all their ſubiects in the feare of the Lord; <hi>Who according to his will worketh in the armie of heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4.32.</note> 
               <hi>and the inhabitants of the earth, and none can ſtay his hand, nor ſay vnto him what doeſt thou?</hi> Whereby both King, and Subiect may know, and ſerue him, <hi>in whoſe hand is their breath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>and all their wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein foraſmuch (my deere Soueraigne I ſpeake it
<pb facs="tcp:23950:3"/>withall reuerence of your excellent Maieſty) as the beſt Kings haue, and do ſometimes ſhew themſelues forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, it were to be wiſht,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Georg. Codinus de efficial. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latii. Con. vulgo Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciopal:</note> the like of that old honourable office, <hi>Of a Kings remembrancer,</hi> were renued, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not ſo much to minde them of mens actions, and exploites, that haue worthily or valiantly behaued, or carried themſelues in peace or in warre, that ſo they might receiue deſerued honour, and recompence: as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and againe to put them in minde of Gods great, and wonderfull workes, that his Maieſtie might haue his due praiſe, and glory neuer ſufficiently to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred.</p>
            <p>But ſith there is no ſuch particular office, which was <hi>Functio optime inſtituta, male exercita, poſſime abolita,</hi> well ordained, ill ordered, and moſt wretchedly aboliſht;<note place="margin">F. Iunij not: in Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropalatem. pag. <hi>313.</hi>
               </note> and that kings are left to be remembrancers vnto themſelues, as of many other things, ſo of the wonderfull workes of GOD, abroad or at home, and that it doeth ſo highly concerne your highneſſe, to make a good vſe, of what hath ſo extraordinarily ſucceeded, within your Maieſties owns kingdome, which is not poſſible without direct no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice. I haue therefore thought it very dutifull, in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulleſt manner, to make knowne to your Highneſſe, and vnder your Highneſſe, gracious approbation, to all your Maieſties ſubiects what, hath ſo wonderfully, and admirably falne out, the time and place forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>Prefixing a remembrance, but in briefe, of two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther memorable, and moſt famous ſpectacles which within the ſpace of forty dayes, haue likewiſe beene, to the admiration of the whole land. I wiſh alſo with the like commemoration, and praiſe of the Almighty power, and neuer fayling goodneſſe of our moſt gratious, and mercifull God: Who for Chriſt his ſake protect, and preſerue your Highneſſe, the Queenes Maieſly, the yong Prince, and all your Highneſſe royall offpring, and iſſue,
<pb facs="tcp:23950:4"/>all your Maieſties kingdomes, dominions, and faithfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſubiects, from the entrage of Satan, and all his limmes, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially from the bloody attempts of all Antichriſts brood: moſt particularly from the deſperate villanies of all ſhorelings ſhauelings, and Ieſuites, this ages (as they are, truely called) King-killers: long to raigne ouer vs, to the glory of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, and the ioy, and comfort of all faithfull and true hearted Subiects.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Highneſſe moſt</hi> humble, and moſt loyall ſubiect <hi>P. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:23950:4"/>
            <head>FEAREFVL NEWES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hrée thinges there are, which in this Ile, within the ſpace of <hi>40.</hi> daies haue very extraordinarily, and wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuccéeded, that deſerue likewiſe more then ordinary remembrance. Of the firſt, withal others that had an vſe of their eye ſight, I was for many nights togither an ey-witneſſe, but not without great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derment. Of the ſecond, I was onely an ear-witneſſe, and that with great thankfulneſſe. Of the laſt, I was both an eare, &amp; an eye-witneſſe with great aſtoniſhment, ſéeing, and hearing the terrible lightning, and thunder, and an admirable effect of them both.</p>
            <p>The two firſt, I will not handle ſo amply, becauſe many others according to their places, and giftes, did with more deepe contemplation waigh the accidents themſelues, and with conſideration can more effectually remember, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them to the glory of God, and the praiſe of his great power, and mercy.</p>
            <p>Of the latter I will (God willing) bée more large, my place, and profeſſion requiring thereof in this kinde a more ample teſtimony, then of any others preſent, from the bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the accident, and action, to the end thereof.</p>
            <p>The firſt therefore worthy of admiration, and ſo of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration, was the ſtreaming, flaming, &amp; burning of the heauens for many nights togither, both before, at, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the time that that horroble, inhumane, and more then butcherly treaſon, (the like whereof was neuer heard of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong infidels) ſhould haue béene executed, to the exting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhing
<pb facs="tcp:23950:5"/>of the light, and taking away of the life of the whole ſtate. The heauens as it were taking a bloudy, and firy impreſſion, and bluſhing as it were at thoſe moſt bloudy attemptes of curſed Caitifes, and of thoſe furious flames which they moſt treacherouſly, were kindling, to the vtter ruinating of their deare cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try and common wealth. Which great worke of God, although all did, or might behold, and ſee with wonderment, yet who could or did know the ende thereof, vntill in the ende the Lord himſelfe made it knowne, and open to the view of all men? And now hauing opened it to all who is ſo blind, (as<note n="*" place="margin">F I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phus in lib. de I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. bel. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> he ſaith, on the tokens that procéeded the taking, and ouerture of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>) neither hauing eies, nor ſoule, as not to ſee, that God hath a ſingular care of mankind, and doth euery where foreſhew betime, what is moſt expedient for them? eſpecially what care the Lord hath of Kings, and kingdomes, and of their regalty, and royalty? That the heauens doe euen take notice, openly foreſhewe, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely bewray, the horrible treacheries, and conſpiracies that ſhalbe in earth, and as it were vnder the earth in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, deſperately complotted, and contriued for the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe, and ruine of their high eſtate, and ſoueraignety, whereon dependeth, as the life of the body on the head, the wealth, and happineſſe of the whole common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>That he that ſeateth, and vnſeateth Kings at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſhould ſo watch ouer their perſons, and places, and watch them, that ſhall ſeeke by moſt vndutifull indignities to wrong their perſons, and places, that where the earth cannot, the heauens ſhall hold out a light, and euen bring to light, thoſe curſed complots, that are in obſcurity moſt deuiliſhly hudled vp, againſt the Crowne and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Lords annointed.</p>
            <p>Is it admirable in the eies of al men almighty God ſhould ſo wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully tender y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good of humane ſocieties, eſpecially of their heads, and gouernours, that the heauens, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpreding
<pb facs="tcp:23950:5"/>the earth, ſhould returne ſuch a reflection of the actions done therein, as not to ſuffer vnreuealed, but pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely by flaming lights therein, to giue a light, to the ſearch, and finding out of that, to their ſingular benefit, whereof otherwiſe to their Imminent danger, they are vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ignorant, is this (I ſay) admirable in the eyes of all, &amp; ought not euery one, and ſhall not all, both King and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, Prince, and people, head, and heart, make a holy, and happy vſe of almighty God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this ſo wonderfull, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable goodneſſe? God forbid elſe. The vſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore béeing manifould, I will heare drawe it to a double head: generall, particular. The generall doeth generally call vpon all men, that fith almighty God hath ſuch a care of all, head, and body, crowne, and foote, that hee hath, and doth not onely inrich vs with infinit good thinges, proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, plenty, peace, (and what not?) all which we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither vtterly vnworthy of: but hath, and doeth alſo day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preuent, and foreſtaie ſo many deſerued euills, reuerting them vpon their heads, that are the inſtruments of ill: all of vs therefore ſhould from the higheſt to the loweſt, from his ſacred Maieſty, that fitteth on the Throne, to the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of water, and hewer of wood know, and acknowledge with feare, and reuerence, the almighty preſence, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of our good God, and alwaies to laud, and praiſe him for his goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>And for that wée are all forgetfull, and dull by nature, each one according to his place, and calling: to prouoke, and ſtirre vp on another, with that of the prophet, not for faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but with affection. <hi>O come and let vs ſing vnto the Lord, let vs heartily reioyce in the ſtrength of our ſaluation.</hi> As this is the generall vſe, ſo the particular is double, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the double eſtate of men, for each King hath his vſe, and euery Subiect his vſe.</p>
            <p>All Kings who acknowledge with reuerence, for their ſoueraigne the King of Kings, haue their vſe of ſingular comfort, and courage euer to behaue themſelues Kingly; not to congratulate this Eſtate, or that perſon at any
<pb facs="tcp:23950:6"/>time, by houering policie, and hidyng piety, conſidering the great founder, and when it pleaſeth him confounder of all Eſtates. and perſons, doth ouer ſhadowe, and ſhelter their thrones, and kingdomes: that ſo long as they ſerue him,<note place="margin">Iob. 5.23.</note> and forward his commands, their is no power there is no policy in earth, or in hell, that ſhall harme their Maieſties one hayre: for all the powers of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and of the earth, are combined, and confederated to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, for the maintainaunce, and vpholding of theyr thrones. But if any ſhal ſo far forget their allegeance to the higheſt, as to ſet themſelues againſt his high commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders on earth, he himſelfe from heauen will ſight againſt them; and cauſe all the reſt of his creatures to crye out vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and to hale them on to due, and moſt deſerued ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution.</p>
            <p>As this is a kingly comfort and incouragement, to kings in their godly gouernment: ſo the ſecond vſe is loyall, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth the ſubiects in their faithfull obedience, to teach, and continue them in loyalty, and fidelity. Is the King ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the king of Kings in his throne, hath the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe thought him ſit viſibly to repreſent vnto thee, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible maieſtie, and wilt not thou in the Lord yeeld vnto him feare, and reuerence? or dareſt thou ſoe, and worme of the earth, whatſoeuer thou art, lift vp I ſay, not a ſword in thy hand, but a thought in thy heart againſt his ſacred po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and gouernment? When the Lord himſelfe ſaith, This man, and his poſterity ſhall raigne ouer thee, and the land of thy ſubiection, and ſhall rule this Empire, this Ile, theſe, and theſe people and nations, art thou ſound, or wilt thou onely be appeacht for a traytor? not onely againſt the Crowne, and dignity, of thy earthly king, who hath power of this thy life, but againſt thy heauenly Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, who hath power (after thy head is taken from thy ſhoulders, thy body vnbowelled, and quartered, and the parts of thy body imparted heere and there, as an horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and odious ſpectacle of thy diſloyalty) to caſt thee, bodye
<pb facs="tcp:23950:6"/>and ſoule into hell? Cannot thy houſe containe thee, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds of fidelity? will not the loue, and credit of thy country, and kindred, the woefull outcries of thy ſweet children, the pitifull lamentations of thy deere wife, if thou haue theſe; or otherwiſe the feare of impriſonment, the Rack, the Halter, and ſo at laſt the terrors of death it ſelfe, terrifie thee from treacherie? yet haue a regard to thy ſoule, ſet not light by that which is the price of the pretious bloud of the ſonne of God. This thou hazardeſt, this without doubt thou wilt caſt away, and caſt thy ſelfe headlong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell, if wilfully, and treaſonably thou ſet thy ſelfe againſt him, whom the Lord hath ſet ouer thée, and the kingdome wherein thou art a ſubiect.</p>
            <p>Subiect thy ſelfe therefore vnder the mighty hand of God, and of him whom that hand hath placed on the throne of the kingdome.</p>
            <p>Conſider with mee (ſaith he) who euer periſht being an Innocent? and conſider with me (ſay I) who euer proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red being a traytor? Since the beaſtly Bull of Pope <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius Quintus;</hi> were there euer heard of ſo many, and ſo bloudy treaſons againſt the ſacred perſons of two chriſtian Princes, as againſt that moſt famous, &amp; péereleſſe Queene, that dead is, and his moſt excellent maieſtie now liuing, &amp; long may he liue, to the comfort of all true-hearted ſubiects, &amp; to the confuſion of all hollow-hearted Traytors. Amen, Amen.</p>
            <p>In this ſucceſſion of times, and treaſons, we ſee by the admirable prouidence of our good God, what hath ſuccée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>And vnleſſe the enemies themſelues, had their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſeard with an hot iron, and were vtterly giuen ouer to a reprobate ſenſe, they muſt needs know and confeſſe, that hitherto they haue, and if they yet perſiſt, ſtill will as Giants fight againſt God.</p>
            <p>Who to the praiſe of his glory, and their euerlaſting ſhame, hath euer, (and I hope euer will) vnbowelled, and
<pb facs="tcp:23950:7"/>ript vp all their freaſons and Traitors. But what ſhall I ſpeake of Traitors, or to traitors, who will neuer make vſe héereof, til the ladder, and halter by lamentable experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teache them; to the turne whereof I leaue them, and turne to you that are true, and faithfull Subiects in déed, exhorting, and charging you in the name of God, by all meanes in theſe Traitorous times, to ſtrengthen, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage your ſelues in your faithfull ſubiection.</p>
            <p>Remember the counſell of God by wiſe King <hi>Salomon,</hi> commaunding all Subiects,<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.20</note> not to intertaine a diſloyall thought againſt their King in their hearts, nor to ſpeak ill in their priuy Chambers, for the foules of the heauen ſhall cary the voice, and the birds of the aire ſhall bewray it.</p>
            <p>And if wée may not admit a diſloyall thought into our hearts, againſt a bad, and a wicked King, how much<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe may wée doe it, againſt ſuch a King (as it hath pleaſed God to giue vs? (immortall thankes bée giuen his Maieſty for it) as is a patron, and patterne of goodneſſe, and vertue to the hole land. <hi>Giue</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt) <hi>to God that which is Gods, to Caeſar that which is Caeſars.</hi> If wée will yéeld to God his, wee muſt yéeld obedience to his word, inioyning vs to feare him, and to honour the King. If we will giue <hi>Caeſar</hi> his, what is more due to the King then loyalty,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.2.3. &amp;c.</note> and ſubiection? This béeing hearty, and inward, will queſtionleſſe draw other duties willingly with it. Who thus béeginneth and continueth in fidelity, and dutifullneſſe, eſpecially in conſcience of Gods commaund, the bleſſing of God ſhall go with him and his: contrarywiſe he that doth not, the curſſe, and vengance of God will finde him out, and follow him at the héeles, and rather then he, &amp; his deſperate deſignes ſhall lie vnreuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the heauens, the foules of the heauen, one, or other of the creatures of God, ſhall giue a light to the opening of it, to his eternal ſhame, and confuſion.</p>
            <p>And hitherto of the firſt admirable action, and accident:
<pb facs="tcp:23950:7"/>the ſecond (wherof I now come to diſcourſe) was the moſt horrible, bloudy, and barbarous treaſon, that euer was heard of, which the fore-remembred fiery, and bloudie ſtreames did accompany, which by the ſingular proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God was detected, defeated, and diuerted to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubuerſion, &amp; confuſion of the wretched Traitors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. It abhorreth me to vſe more words of it &amp; yet what words are able to expreſſe the horror of it? I will onely content my ſelfe, to make ſome good vſe of this their damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ill.</p>
            <p>The firſt reſpecteth the helliſh Traitors, and hel-bounds themſelues with all their complices: the ſecond, all againſt whom that deſperate, and diuelliſh proſcription was made. For the wicked complotters themſelues, and their wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed complices, I meane al Papiſts, their former traitorly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, with this more then brutiſh, ſurpaſſing all others their bloudy, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>kiſh enterpriſes: not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bly bewr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieth the fruit of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Popiſh religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and doeth notoriouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime vnto vs, what we are to expect at their Traiterous hands, ſo long as they abide, and breath a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng vs. Who ſo with attention readeth the hiſtories either diuine, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, he ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Godly pitty hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aies accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied true piety, ſo idolatry, and cruelty haue commonly gone togither. And if euer any idolaters were famous, or rather infamous for truculency, and inhumanity, then without doubt the men eating Papiſts. I néed not inſtant héerein, that one bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne of the <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Monuments</hi> hath caſed me of this l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bor, and doth entry where fore them for it. Neither is it any maruaile they ſo malice the booke, and the man for his booke, that they ceaſe not to inueigh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his dead bons which if they were within their reach, as <hi>P. Phagius,</hi> and <hi>Bucers</hi> were, ſhould not ſmell of the ſmoake, but ſmoake in the fire. Then which what can be imagined more cruell? what greater inhumanity can be deuiſed?</p>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:23950:8"/>
               <l>Corpora maegnanimo ſatis eſt proſtraſſe leoni,</l>
               <l>Pugna ſuum finem, cum iacit hoſtis habet:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At lupus, et turpes inſtant morientibus vrſi,</l>
               <l>Et quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> minor nobititate fera est.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lion ſtout doth reſt,</l>
               <l>when he hath feld to geound</l>
               <l>His foe, when he lyeth flatte,</l>
               <l>an end of fight is found.</l>
               <l>The Woulfe and filthy Beares,</l>
               <l>doe rend the dying beaſt,</l>
               <l>As each is cruell more,</l>
               <l>that is in courage leaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>They are worſe then the Lion, Woulfe, or Beare, of which, the worſt preieth only on the dead fleſh, but theſe after the fleſh is rotten, ceaſe not to prey on the dead bones. What maruaile, ſith they pray to dead bones and ſtones, and what not? Idolatry, and cruelty may not, they cannot be at any time parted or diuorced.</p>
            <p>As their cruelty is firſt noted, and but noted, becauſe it is otherwiſe notorious in all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns eyes, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euer before, yet now by their laſt more then heatheniſh, &amp; brutiſh cruelty, ſo ſecondly let vs ſee; what we are to expect from their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, ſo long as they continue among vs.</p>
            <p>It is obſerued as a ſingular point of wiſedome, to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee what will fall out, the foole onely looking foorth right, and to that which is before his feete, not comparing times paſt, with the preſent; and both theſe, with that which is to come, thereby to prouide for his owne good, and preuent his owne harme, which if we wil do with wiſdome, and circumſpection, in this caſe of Ieſus Chriſts moſt profeſt, and our heauy enemies the Papiſts, we may eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly coniecture what their future, and after behauiour will be; by their former, and preſent, cruell, and Caniballike car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23950:8"/>
            <p>If a ſhe Beare robd of her whelpes, or a hungry woulfe, will not prey on the ſilly Lambe ſhe meeteth in her way, then may we truſt the Popiſh crewe, and ſuffer them to continue, and range vp and downe among vs.</p>
            <p>The ſhee woulfe of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath had heretofore, and now for their treaſons is like to haue, ſuch a loſſe of her whelpes; whether ſhe, and hers yet liuing, will not ſeeke reuenge, I will not make queſtion, leaſt I ſhould ſéeme to doubt, whether a Woulfe, be a Woulfe, and <hi>Rome</hi> the ſame to day that it was yeſterday:<note place="margin">Reuel. 17.9.</note> for certenly ſo long as ſhe pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth on ſeauen hills, ſhe will either ouercrowe the Kings of the earth, or ſéeke to plucke their Crownes from their heads,</p>
            <p>And what ſhe doth, ſhee will teach all her broode,<note place="margin">Reuel. 17.16.17.18. Reuel. 18.6 Reuel. 18.6 eDut. 13.1</note> and chickens to doe, vntill the Kings of the earth, according to Gods fore councell, and iuſtice, and according to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in that behalfe, ioyne together, and execute the wrath of God vpon her, and her adherents. Which if al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, command them to doe in the head, I deſire to know what they ought to do in the members? Euery profeſt idolater, by the lawe of God is to dye, but the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are profeſt Idolaters: the aſſumption, or minor propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition will be doubted of; I will not therefore conclude, till I haue ſtrengthened, and confirmed it, knitting it vp after this ſort.</p>
            <p>If Papiſts be the groſeſt idolaters that euer were, then idolaters, but the former is as true, as the ſeuen hild citty, is the ſeat of Antichriſt, <hi>ergo</hi> the latter as ſhe ſhall certen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be burnt with fire, for ſtrong is the Lord God that will do it. The antecedent will not bee graunted mee: for the conſequent; S. <hi>Iohn</hi> warranteth me: I therefore fortifie it thus. All they that worſhip ſo baſe a thing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a peece of bread for the maker of heauen, and earth, idle Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ruſty nailes, rotten timber, and olde ragges, are the groſeſt Idolaters that euer were; but the Papiſts doe all theſe, therefore they are the groſeſt
<pb facs="tcp:23950:9"/>Idolaters that euer were. And now I conclude, Papiſts ought by the law of God to die. But me ſeemeth I ſee ſome man ſteppe forth, now I haue concluded pleading for Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and Papiſtry, denying my propoſition the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of all: and yet me thinketh it cannot ſtand faſter then on the eternall, and vnalterable word of God. But ſayth he, it is one of <hi>Moyſes</hi> iudicialls. Is it indeed <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and not Almighty Gods? He reioyneth therefore, yes, and thoſe Iudicialls were temporary, and for the ſtate of the Iewes, and taken away by the appearing of Chriſt. To this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioinder, I adioyne, that Chriſt ſayth no ſuch thing, but that he came, not to take away the law, but to fulfil the law. He came to deſtroy, and take away the works of darkenes, not to make a way for the workes of darkenes: which he muſt needs doe, if he ſhould either take the ſword out of the Magiſtrates hands, or giue it in his hand, there to ſuffer it ruſt in the ſheath, and not draw it forth againſt offendors. And I pray you in good part, againſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould he vſe it, if not againſt Idolaters, the greateſt &amp; notorieſt Traytors againſt God, and his glory, that the earth yeeldeth?</p>
            <p>Shall Kings draw the ſword which the Lord hath put in their hands and that moſt iuſtly, for the cutting off, of them that complot treaſons againſt their owne perſons, and ſhall they be leſſe zealous in the Lords cauſe, then in their owne? But what ſpeake I of the Lords cauſe onely, when in this caſe of the Papiſts, there is a double treaſon, firſt againſt God by their idolatry, next againſt the King by their diſloyalty. This latter I affirme, &amp; confirme it thus. Whoſoeuer holdeth the Popes ſupremacie, is a Traytor to the King, but all Papiſts hold the Popes ſupremacie: My aſſumption will heere againe be baited at, I will ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bar it thus. If euery Chriſtian haue his name for that in trueth he acknowledgeth Chriſt his head, then euery <hi>Papiſta,</hi> Papiſt hath his name from <hi>Papa</hi> the Pope, for that he acknowledgeth him his head, but the former is true therefore the latter. So that if once I beare him ſay he is a
<pb facs="tcp:23950:9"/>Papiſt, I can truely ſay by and by he is a traytor. But wée will haue a ſhift for this, he is no Papiſt, if there be ſuch danger in the notation of the name, but a Catholicke, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you it is now well amended, as one waſhing off the filth of his face with inke.</p>
            <p>From whence I pray you cometh this name? what ſoundeth it? After this ſort, whoſoeuer holdeth the Popes ſupremacie, is a traitor, euery Catholick holdeth the Popes ſupremacie: my aſſumption neede here no more words, for this very name ſelleth me, that he holdeth the vniuerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo the vniuerſall authoritie of the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> And this will alwayes be the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the dirige, a Papiſt, a catholick, a traytor, a traytor. But it may be our language is harſh, and barren, giuing graceleſſe names to gracious men: will the ſmooth Latin, lend vs a couple of names in ſteed of them, to ſteed theſe men, for I would ſaine tid my ſelfe of them? What ſay you to <hi>Pontificius,</hi> and <hi>Papicola,</hi> will either of theſe better Papiſt, or catholick? Surely no; neuer a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell better hearing: for when all commeth to all, either hée muſt forget his Papiſtry, or hee can neuer forgoe his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery. Notwithſtanding al this, if he wil continue a Papiſt, and ſo his treaſon, and ſo his double treaſon, firſt againſt god, next againſt the King, what remaineth but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of a treator. Yea but we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne papiſtry of cruelty, and what were this to execute all Papiſts: firſt therefore we muſt know a difference betweene one that is fooliſhly Popiſh, and that ſmacketh of the corrupt dregs of <hi>Rome,</hi> and an other, that hath drunken of the wine of her fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, péeuiſhly popiſh, &amp; a peruerſe papiſt, a young Cubbe, and an old Fox, one that is créeping out of the ſhell, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother that is fledge, for when I ſpeake of a Papiſt, which inſtantly ecchoeth a traytor, &amp; by and by calleth for a hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I meane ſuch a one as is a true Papiſt, a Catholick, <hi>Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tificius, Papicola,</hi> that hath the grounds, &amp; is grounded in the fundamentall points of his rebellion, I ſhould ſay his
<pb facs="tcp:23950:10"/>religion, for as ſure as the Lord liueth, if he be a reſolute papiſt, he is an abſolute traytor to God and his King: &amp; it was neuer heard of, that to execute him ſhould ſauour any way of extremity, and crulty, but of moſt iuſt ſeuerity. Nay rather to ſpare ſuch a one, as a rotten member, to the vtter hazard of the hole body, may be well accounted in humanity &amp; more then deſperate folly. God almighty, in whoſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d are the hearts of al men to turne them whether it pleaſeth him, ſo in wiſdome direct his vicegerents here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that they may in their ſeueral kingdoms, do that which may moſt ſerue for his glory, and the good of their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall eſtates. Hitherto of the traitors, that did complot the former horrible treaſon, and their complices: now for the vſe we are to make, againſt whom, and whoſe good, it was moſt deuiliſhly complotted, and deſperately contriued.</p>
            <p>Which is likewiſe double, the firſt, reſpecting Gods iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, the ſecond, his mercy. Concerning his Iuſtice, let vs know and remember with profit, that hee by the hand of theſe vniuſt wretches, ſhaking his rod vnto vs, did therby ſhew what we for our many ſinnes had iuſtly deſerued: Euen all of vs to feele, and ſee an vtter demolition, and deſolation of our ſtate, and common wealth.</p>
            <p>For although theſe more then wicked traitors, had no iuſt cauſe, nor occaſion to draw them on, but moſt deſperately by the inſtigation of the deuill, and their deuiliſh madnes, were carried on headlong to attempt, and enterpriſe ſo horrible a treaſon, the like whereof no hiſtory doth affoord, as at an inſtant to kill the King, the Queene, the Prince, and all the flower of the Church, and common wealth, &amp; that after a moſt helliſh and fearfull manner, by blowing them vp in the aire, &amp; ſo to leaue the commonwealth as a forſaken widow, proſtituting her to be deflowred, defaced, and deſolated by the bloody hands of baſtard children at home, and the furious inuaſions of forrein tirants, and ſo to make her a terror to herſelf, &amp; a terrible ſpectacle of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame miſery, &amp; calamity to the whole world: howſoeuer I ſay, they had no cauſe to do or attempt this, yet we may acknowledg, &amp; confeſſe that by the iuſt iudgment of God, all this, and more (if more might bee) might haue come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:23950:10"/>vs, and ouertaken vs. But almighty God euen in the mideſt of his iudgement, remembring mercy, did only ſhake the rod at vs, and then caſt it into the fire. That ſo long as we liue, and our poſterity after vs, in that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, which by the iuſtice of God wee had almoſt loſt, but by his mercy yet poſſeſſe, &amp; inioy, and I hope ſhal to the ende of the world, maugre the malice of the deuill, we may learne to feare Gods Iuſtice, to loue his mercy, and ſo for his iuſtice, and mercy, to feare, and loue him, and to praiſe him with the prophet in that excellent ſong. If the the Lord had not beene on our ſide (may wee now ſay) If the Lord had not bin on our ſide, when men roſe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, and ſo forth to the end of that pſalme. Who ſo maketh not theſe profitable vſes, of this wonderfull deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the lord but runneth on in ſin without remorce, let him remember what Chriſt ſaid to the man deliuered from his malady, go and ſinne no more, leaſt a worſe thing happen vnto thee. And here an end of the two firſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull accidents, I meane an end of my diſcourſe thereof: but I hope the inhabitants of this land will neuer ceaſe, with thankfullnes to God, to remember his iuſtice, and mercy therein neuer ſufficiently to be praiſed.</p>
            <p>O Eternal God, creator of heauen, and earth, &amp; in Ieſus Chriſt my moſt mercifull father, I thy vnworthy ſeruant returne vnto thy diuine maieſty moſt humble and hearty thanks, as for all other thy vnſpeakable mercies, ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the great and wonderful deliuerance of my ſelfe, and many other of thy poore and ſinfull creatures, from the rage, and force of the horrible thunder and lightning, which of late thou didſt ſend amongſt vs. The true report whereof, ſith I am herein to deliuer to thy ſeruant King <hi>Iames,</hi> whom thou by thy almighty prouidence haſt made thy vicegerent in this mighty empire, and ſo vnto thy people his ſubiects: ſo ſanctify (good Lord) my memory, and meditation, and therewith all my report and relation, that the truth herein beeing effectually deliuered, it may redound to the glory of thy great name, the profit of thy beloued children, &amp; the terror of thy profeſt enemies. Amen</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23950:11"/>
            <p>Now I come to the third wonderfull, and terrible acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, whereof I was both an eare, and an eye-witneſſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt I will according to the truth, deliuer the report thereof, and next make ſuch profitable vſes, as ſo great, and wonderfull a worke doth require. Firſt therefore where a report is to be made of an action done, the time, and place are of no ſmall moment, for the euidence of the matter. The time therefore was on Thurſday being the <hi>28.</hi> of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber laſt, about a moneth after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſaid fearful flaming of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauens, and moſt horrible treaſon complotted &amp; detected. The place was at <hi>Ouelſtone</hi> in the county of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> ſcituated ſome eight miles from the famous citie of <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> and two miles from <hi>Auſt,</hi> which is well knowne, in regard of the often tranſportation, and paſſage there ouer the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of <hi>Seuerne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This for the time and place, when, and where this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull worke of God, was by his al nighty hand wrought, and done: now for the action, and worke it ſelfe. The mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the foreſaid day being lowring, and ſad, did yet a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after eight, begin to ſmile, and looke ſome-what cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full toward the eaſt: which was indéed but a ſmile, and for a very ſmal time, for euen anone before nine of the clock, the weſt as it were enuying the eaſts meriment, ſendeth me vp with a ſtrong winde, a moſt darke mantle, which ouerſpred the whole heauens, as if the ſunne had vpon ſome ſudden feare, ſodenly retired, and againe hid it ſelfe vnder our hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, giuing place to the darke night, to wrap vp all thinges in her black mourning gowne. So darke and blacke was it, that but for the note of the time, it was hard to iudge whether it were day, or night: yet after halfe an howre, or there about, this black maſke was againe taken off, and the heauens begin to ſmouth vp, and cléere their countenance, the ſunne ſending forth from the ſouth, his goulden raies for an howre and halfe: which the north diſdayning with a moſt ſcornfull lower, thinking it ſelfe wronged, as the weſt did before, and terribly menacing the ſouth (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:23950:11"/>the winde ſtood betwene them to ſtay the quarel) with a moſt terrible and ougly viſage. Neither was it ſatiſfied with threatning lookes, but her fearefull forces come on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, admitting yet betwéen, them &amp; the ſun, a ſhort parle, made knowne by a goodly, and beautifull rainbow. The ſight whereof did not a little comfort mee, notwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frowning face of the heauens, did otherwiſe pretend ſome fearefull euent: for beholding the worlds Sacrament, I remembred not onely that couenant of God, which it doth ſeale vnto, but his other couenant made with vs in Chriſt, whereby hée hath bound himſelfe, and that with an oath, to be our God, and wee (euen as many of vs as by faith ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the force and fruit of it) to be his people. And that therefore though eaſt, and weſt, north and ſouth, heauen, and earth, ſhould bee iumbled, and tumbled togither, yet the anchor of our hope, and happineſſe, being caſt within the veale, and founded on Chriſt the vnmoouable rock, could not faile, nor deceiue, nor be deceiued.</p>
            <p>With this or the like meditation, I paſt from vnder the Canopy of the open heauens, vnder the roofe of the houſe.</p>
            <p>Where after a very little while, being ſet at dinner, the terrible darkneſſe, that was in the North, ſo gathered on the ſouth, that it became very darke, conſidering the time of the day, and the cléere light that was but a little before. But the thick cloudes had indéed their burden, wherof they haſted to be eaſed, for down falleth with a boiſterous winde a very plentifull haile, which with the abundance (for it was better then halfe a foot thick on the ground, euery where after the tempeſt, which laſted a quarter of an houre or there about) and the winde made a very terrible rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, which was accompanied with fearefull flaſhes of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſome thrée, or fower claps of more then ordinary thunder.</p>
            <p>Whereof I tooke occaſion of talke, to the gentle woman of the houſe, and her yong plants, which (being fiue ſonnes
<pb facs="tcp:23950:12"/>with the ſonne of a friend) ſat at table with vs, to this effe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> That the Atheiſts of the world, and ſuch as did not know, acknowledge, and feare God, had great cauſe to be terrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to tremble, at ſuch terrors of his: but for ſuch as did truely feare God, they need not be appaled, or diſmaid at it, conſidering they know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, it came from God their grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous father in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>She replyed with a remembrance of the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that if this, then much more terrible, would the daye of the Lord be vnto ſuch, as did not know God in Chriſt, and in him, had a feeling of his fatherly loue.</p>
            <p>In the middeſt of our talke, behold, there flameth in a wonderfull flaſh of Lightning, ſeconded with as horrible a report of extraordinary Thunder, as I thinke any man liuing hath heard. It was not as the manner is of thunder, a ratling and rumbling noyſe drawne in length, but as if a thouſand tun waight had falne from a loft vpon a loft able to indure the weight of it, making a moſt inexplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vnſpeakeable thumpe and hownce, to them that are vnder it. Such was the furious and fearefull report of this terrible clap of thunder, wherewith according to the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of this corrupt fleſh, I was toucht, but not without aſſured hope in God, vſing the words of the Pſalme. <hi>Powre out thy wrath, O Lord vpon the heathen, that know thee not, and vpon the kingdomes that call not on thy name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The table beeing taken vp, and God for his mercies, praiſed, I betooke me euen vpon <hi>12.</hi> a clocke to my ſchoole, where finding my ſchollers amazed with what had euen then paſt, I put them in mind of that I had ſpoken in the morning (for with our morning prayer, wee had the firſt Chapter to the <hi>Romanes</hi> read) concerning the two means whereby God maketh himſelfe knowne vnto the world, his word, and his workes According to the preſent occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I vrged the ſecond, which I had that very day deliuered out of thoſe words of the Apoſtle, in the <hi>20.</hi> verſe, for the inuiſible things of him, that is his eternall power &amp; God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,
<pb facs="tcp:23950:12"/>are ſeene by the creation of the world, béeing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his workes to the intent they ſhould bee without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe.</p>
            <p>But in the midſt of my ſpéech, I heard the Belles knole extraordinarily, and ſending one forth to enquire the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he preſently returned anſwer, the Steeple was a fire.</p>
            <p>So concluding abruptly, and paſſing forth at doores, I ſawe it was no falſe report of a fained fire. For behold, the force of Gods terrible voice, had ſhaken, rifted, and rent the Towre of ſtone, whereon the Spier of Lead of a great height ſtood toward the Weſt, from the reſt of the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, almoſt to the roofe of the Church. And as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red afterward, all the weſt end of the Church was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhaken, which was ſo much the more to be wondred at, as it beeing cruſht in diuers places, as a rotten apple: it was onely ſo done within, and no appearance of it without: and of thrée great glaſſe Windowes that ſtand in that end, not one of them hurt by it, either in the Glaſſe or lights, Albeit the wall were ſhaken both immediatly aboue and vnder them, the ſtronger being hurt, and the weaker ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping harmeleſſe.</p>
            <p>So powerfull and prouident is Almighty God, that he ſtriketh and leaueth vnſtriken where he will, and whom he will, that ſtrength to him is weakeneſſe, and weakeneſſe to him is ſtrength.</p>
            <p>And although this Thundring voyce of Almighty God, did no where ſhewe ſo terrible an effect, as on and in the Church, yet without the Church, in the Field and in the houſes neere, an extraordinary preſence of his power, not without his mercie, was ſenſibly to bee perceiued by diuerſe, whom it caſt, one hither, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thither, and ſome downe, but hurt neither man, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, child, nor any liuing creature els, for ought that I haue heard.</p>
            <p>As this was the effect of the terrible Thunder, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:23950:13"/>his fearefull fire (the lightning I meane) had fiered the ſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, about thrée quarters of a yard beneath the foote of the barre, whereon the weathercocke pearcht, which fearefull fire, conſidering the powerfull hand that had kindled it, the matter whereon, and the bellowes which did blowe it, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at firſt a ſtrong weſterne wind, how it did rage, they may wel imagine that ſawe it not, which they may farther vnderſtand by this, that within the ſpace of two houres, it did deuoure, conſume, melt, and throwe downe al the tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, lead, and irons that were from the top of the Stéeple, (being as I haue ſaid of a great height) to the towre of ſtone, and in other thrée howres, did burne to the ground, melt, and caſt downe with an vnreſiſtable force, all the lofts, timbers, ſtockes, and wheeles of fiue very tunenable but often abuſed bells.</p>
            <p>The Clocke, which before had notified pretious time, calling on men as it were to take time, and to take heede of the abuſe of ſo excellent a treaſure, was likewiſe hereby ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced. The Chancell, through the flered timbers and fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands, which fell from the Steeple, on the roofe of it, was fiered and defaced. As it was very probable, the Church would haue bene alſo with the like, had not the winde carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the rage of the fire ſo much on the Chancell, which ſtood on the Eaſtſide fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church, which is ſeated on the weſt. But the fire it ſelf did not much harme the church, the moſt hurt it receiued being great, was from the hands of men, who fearing what was likely, that the rage of the flames, would haue had the like force on the Church, as it had on the ſtéeple; ſought to ſaue what might be. They ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ript vp and caſt out almoſt all the ſeates, and vncoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the three Iles of the Church in the middle, in hope to ſaue, if it might be, that halfe which was weſtermoſt, if the other halfe, next the ſteeple were fired. But their labour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed turned to loſſe, as it fell out, for God by his good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, did not onely reſtraine the rage of the fire, from the Church which was on the Weſt, but likewiſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:23950:13"/>néere, moſt admirably, eſpecially, from the miniſters which ſtood ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder the mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of the fire, and the winde. that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thouſand ſtakes of fire might be ſeene, to light a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ng his wood, on his hay, &amp; corne mowes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſoon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer almoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as about his houſe, and yet ſo gratious is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> onely, I think did him not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of hurt. In the meane ſeaſon, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not withſtanding this ſo mani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able a toolke of God, in weath ſpeaking vnto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>n, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch ſort, as you haus heard that ſawe it not, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> from heaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, of many that ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſcarce one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt many, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſhap is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, what a miſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap> here, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hap, what bad forfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, wiſh ſuch heatho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſh ſpeec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſphears of heauen were the wheeles of fortune, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the clouds, hayle; lightning, thunder, and alt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> God elſe, were but a caſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hazard. So little we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected eſt hee with the great power of God, or the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> their owne great ſinnes, yea I dare ſay (and yet I thinke before the Lord I ſay the truth more did truely for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent what they haue done ſince I know not) bewailt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e or their ſweet ring of Bels, which the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e wrath of God, would no longer ſuffer to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>angle, then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their ignorance of God, and his goodnes, or their vnthankfulnes, or for any other ſin, which was doth the cauſe of this, and is the cauſe of all other his iudgements. And leaſt I ſhould ſéeme to ſpeake without booke h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> I will alleadge that reſtimony, which is without exception, the greateſt of al other, of the aboundance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>the heart, the mouth ſpeaketh. The truth whereof not beeing doubted, then I ſay, it is an vndoubled truth I haue affirmed, for I heard with mine eares, diuers lament the death (as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) of their Belles, but no one; there ſo much as mention, the guilt or puniſhment of ſinne.</p>
            <p>And if they that were preſent ſpectators, and had a ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all intereſt as it were in ſo manifeſt, and publicke a pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent
<pb facs="tcp:23950:14"/>of Gods wrath reuealed from heauen, made ſo little vſe of it, what great cauſe is there, ſome ſpeciall vſes be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ript vp, as well for them that are nere, as for them that are farder of: I come therefore to the vſe. Which is double firſt, in regard of places, ſecondly of perſons, for places it beeing a towre, and a Steeple of great height, proudly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring as it were, and aduancing it ſelfe in the apre, that was thus fearefully ſtrucken with the piercing force of thunder and lightning, as it many times hath falne out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nes the tower of <hi>Babell</hi> began to bee founded, that God writeth confuſion on models erected with ambition, it is a document to all places to take heed of the like ambitious fully, leaſt they haue the like pernicious fall. It is fayned of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, that it creepeth at firſt on the ground, but at laſt it r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſteth on the top of high topt turrets, but for the fame of Gods wrath lighting on places, moſt while it ariſeth from the ouerturning of that, which hath beene turretted &amp; rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp aloſt. That where the proud ſpiers ſeems to threaten the heauens, they are by the heauens ouer topt, and turned topſey turney to the ground. And as this is exempliſted in proud towers, and turrets, ſo may it bee in trees, that pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out of the earth, wil at the length aduance themſelues ſo haughtily, as if they diſdained the drops that come from the clouds ſhould light on their crownes. But it is in vaine to ſpeake of the places without the perſons, for though god write confuſion on them, they know not ne feele their owne pride or perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; which lighteth on them, not for any ſin of theirs, for they are vnreaſonable and vnſenſible, but for the ſin of mens perſons, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath indued with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon &amp; vnderſtanding, &amp; vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; vſe of his other creatures, for the abuſe wherof he doth in iuſtice, not onely ſometimes ſet the ſtampe of his wrath vpon their perſons, but more often in mercy doth ſpare their perſons, &amp; brand it in the other creatures, that he hath giuen for their profit or pleaſure. I come therefore to the perſonal vſes hereof, which ſhalbe threefold, according to mens thrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold eſtate, higheſt, loweſt, or betwéene both.</p>
            <p>Men of the firſt order, and ranck, I do moſt humbly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat
<pb facs="tcp:23950:14"/>often and againe to remember, who hath ſo highly aduanced them, and whereunto; for the forgetfullneſſe of theſe two points, is followed with an impotency of mind, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> archenimye of moderation, &amp; the moſt potent procurer of the haſty downfall of their high eſtate.<note place="margin">Prou. 8.15.</note> For if they did euer remember of whom they hold their places, and of what importance, that it is the ſonne of GOD by whom kings raigne and ſtateſmen decree iuſtice, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> princes hold their principality, and all the good Iudges of the earth: and as by the ſonne of God they are placed, the importance of their places to bee ſuch, as <hi>Moyſes</hi> the beſt commaunder, on that euer was, groned vnder the burden of it: and <hi>Salomon</hi> maketh it a matter of impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, for any man to diſcharge it,<note place="margin">1. King 3.9</note> without more then hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ability. If they did remember (I ſay) theſe things to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither with the peril, whereto great men in that they are great, are ſubiect, could pride ſo haue preuaild with many of them as it hath, as <hi>Pharoah, Nebucadnezar, Herod,</hi> &amp; not onely with ſuch bad gouernors but with the beſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Hezechiah?</hi> Which deſeaſe the Lord who knoweth the hearts of men, foreſeeing how it would infect, did before hand preſcribe a diet, and gaue an an tedate, which may be there more fitly &amp; profitably ſeene then here remembred. And ſith it is the Lords preſcription,<note place="margin">Deu. 17.19.20.</note> it is not without manifeſt danger to be neglected, but to be vſed of men in higheſt places, as they loue their own health and happines. A word to the wiſe, I will therfore conclude, this firſt vſe, vnto men of the firſt roome, as Kings, their great councellers and aſſiſtants, with the ſpeach of the Kingly prophet <hi>Dauid;</hi> and leauing them vnto the grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bleſſing of God, moſt humbly take my leaue.<note place="margin">Pſ. 138.4.</note> All the Kings of the earth ſhal praiſe thee O Lord: for they haue heard the words of thy mouth. And they ſhall ſing of the waies of the Lord, becauſe the glory of the Lord is great: for the lord is high, yet be beholdeth the lowly, but the proud he knoweth a far of. Now I deſcend to men of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ck &amp; order, who are as models of means ſtate, neither ſo high, that they ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the mercy of euery threat of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayre, nor ſo low, that they are ſubiect to euery inundation of the water.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23950:15"/>
            <p>Who as they ſtand betwéene two, ſo they muſt make this vſe to take héed, eſpecially of two faults, enuy toward their ſuperiours, or diſdaine to their inſcriours. Enuy nor emulate they muſt not any way their ſuperiours, nor the higheſt places poſſeſt by the higheſt perſonages, ſith it is the good will of God to erect both.</p>
            <p>The places are of great importance, poſſeſſors of them are ſubiect to much perill, as the high ſtéeples to the force of all bluſtring ſtormes. They watch when others ſléepe, they faſt when others eate, they carke when others are ſecure, they beare the wood, and others warme themſelues by the fire, they ſowe the corne and others reape the harueſt, yet al this while for recompence, their places, perſons, and liues, are aimed at, that their eſtates are beleigered with millions of miſerable labours, and feares of extreme loſſes. In the meane ſeaſon, thou doeſt ſléepe when thou wilt, eate what thou haſt, reſt ſecure, warme thée, ſow and reape, &amp; though theſe be great bleſſings, to theſe is added hearts eaſe, if God giue thée a heart to conceiue thine owne good. Thou what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou art of this order, haſt the goulden meane, if thou demeane thy ſelfe accordingly, the goulden meane I ſay, which <hi>Agur</hi> the ſonne of <hi>lakeh,</hi> did ſo importune the Lord for.</p>
            <p>Read the place with attention, I leaue the ſearch and ſwéetneſſe of it, to thy ſelfe and thine owne experience. In the meane time, as men of the ſecond ranke muſt for many reſpects, without enny but with ſingular ſubmiſſion, &amp; reuerence, demeane themſelues to them that are aboue, ſo they muſt auoide all diſdaine and contempt of them that are belowe.</p>
            <p>This latter they will the ſooner be drawne to do, if they remember the double accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they are to yéeld, of the which, the one though for a time delaid neuer faileth. If they wrong, deſpite, or deſpiſe their inferiours, they ſhal anſwere to their ſuperiours on earth, who with King <hi>Dauid</hi> ſing of mercy, and iudgement: of mercy to the mercifull, of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:23950:15"/>and iuſtice to the cruell. But if either by their owne ability of friends, money, flattery, or any other indirect meanes: or the inability of the oppreſſed, not able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, or follow it; they foredoe, and foregoe this account in earth, yet certenly they ſhall not faile to come before the heauenly iudge, who telleth them plainely before hand, whereto they ſhall truſt. He that deſpiſeth the poore repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth him that made him. And thinkeſt thou hee will beare reproches at thy hands, &amp; not pay thee home? Or wilt thou not remember that the law of God, and nature, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thée, if thou hurt him, whom both of them command thée to helpe? I might heere open a ſea of reaſons, and al le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations in this behalfe, to diſwade men from contempt, &amp; diſdaine of the meaneſt, and to perſwade them to pitty, and compaſſion. But one ſhall be to them and me, inſteed of all. It is taken from that ſolemne manner of procéeding in generall conuocation, of all before the great iudge, at the fearefull day of iudgement, when Chriſt ſhal denounce that terrible doome <hi>(Depart from me ye curſed into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire, prepared for the deuill and his angells)</hi> not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them onely that haue pluckt the meat from the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, taken away drinke from the thirſty, wrongd the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, drawn vniuſtly the ſkinne as it were ouer mens eares, and ſo afflicted their ſoules and bodies, for there is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry nor queſtion made of them, being <hi>Ipſo facto</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to hell: but this heauy doome they ſhall alſo haue, that haue not fed the hungry, giuen drinke to the thirſtie, lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſtraunger, cloathed the naked, viſited the ſicke, and ſuch like. Thou ſeeſt how the caſe ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, weigh the truth by the aucthority; and practiſe it for thy owne ſafely. So in the name of God, I exhort thee not to enuie, but to honour thy ſuperiours, not to deſpiſe but to helpe thy inferiours, of whom commending thée to Gods grace in Chriſt Ieſus, I come now briefly to ſpeake. Theſe therfore to the <hi>2.</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer eſtates, are as poore cuttages to the higheſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urrets, as mold-hills to the mighty mountaines, the ſhrubbes to the
<pb facs="tcp:23950:16"/>Cedars of <hi>Libanon.</hi> Yet though they be ſuch, the higheſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, may not ſet them at naught, nor the ſecond ſort little account of them. Foraſmuch as the lower they ſtand, and the leſſe able they are, to help and right themſelues, the more doth the Lord tender their caſe, and the more ſeuerely wil be reuenge their wrongs. But they haue a fault, which if they would amend, notwithſtanding their pouerty, they might be paſſing happy, and that is impatiency. Men in the higheſt places, except god grace them, extraordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly labour of impotencie of mind, and cannot beare their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, or their eſtates abide with them for pride: and men of the loweſt places, except God comfort them, exceedingly labour of impotencie of mind, and cannot brooke their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for want of patience. Whereas this beeing poſſeſt, they would not onely comfortably indure, the indifferent calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their eſtate, but by their hearty and humble prayers vnto God (as in duty they are bound) eaſe much their ſuperiours, thoſe eſpecially y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt places, moſt traueld and troubled, and therefore néeding moſt the aſſiſtance of their godly praiers. The God of patience, grant this vnto them, and ſo vnto all eſtates, conditions, and ſorts of men, ſo to carry, demeane, and behaue themſelues, as in his glorious preſence, who wil bleſſe all them that feare him both ſmall and great.<note place="margin">Pſ. 115.13.</note> Here an end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> threefold vſe deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to the thrée eſtates of men, concerning the third wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full worke of God, and ſo of the three admirable actions: Which beeing three, and all very extraordinary, are a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient teſtimony againſt all, that hearing thereof, will not yet in time repent and amend their liues, but haue their eares and hearts ſo ſhut vp, and hardned againſt the power of God, reuealed both in his words and works; that nothing wil deterre them from ſinne, and draw them to godlines, til Chriſt come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, with thouſand thouſands of angels, in flaming fire to iudge the world:<note place="margin">Reuel. 22.</note> which as it haſteth, ſo haſten Lord Ieſu, for thy promiſe ſake: ſurely I come quickly, Amen Euen ſo come Lord Ieſus. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hallelu-iah.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:23950:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
